[Music]
hello everyone this is Arry
I'm a person and I think things and I
feel things and I have a body I have to
manage that all the time I have emotions
got to manage those all the time it's
weird it's really weird existence as
strange as fuck but there are people you
come across that make it a little bit
easier to deal with and help you feel
your existence acknowledge the things
that you feel the things that you think
the person that you are and the things
that you're not these are moments in
relation that are very authentic these
are authentic relations there are
different frameworks that people have
come up with different tools that we can
use to communicate with one another that
help us feel more seen that help us
acknowledge who we are and what our
experience is to help bring into the
light the shadow parts of ourselves that
we don't like to look at that we try to
close off from that we try to mask
you could call these authentic relating
games frameworks and the guest on
today's episode is my friend guy singing
stock guys the founder of what is called
circling circling is one of these tools
circling is a framework in which we can
see each other better and be more
authentically connected to one another
and not to fix each other this is not a
therapy this is not a this is not a way
for us to drastically improve ourselves
directly this is a way just to hear each
other just to provide a space for us to
say what's real in us and for us to
train the muscle the muscle the muscle
of truthfulness guy has been doing this
for a really long time since I was a wee
little lad
he's very insightful and he's so funny
his humor is something that I think
makes him great at this and they haven't
been in a circle with guy yet that is
soon to come I'm sure yes we've been
sending voice memos back and forth all
week that just have me rolling laughing
he's so funny
[Music]
so it's an interesting topic really and
if you've been listening to the podcast
for any length of time one of the things
that I hope you are noticing is that I
am trying my best to be honest with you
I am trying my best to be earnest to be
truthful to be transparent in the
moments that I don't know what the fuck
is going on when I don't feel totally
confident when I feel scared when I feel
confused this podcast is literally a
journal of my transformation
intellectually emotionally spiritually I
am picking these guests out because
there are areas of my life that I know
are calling me to grow and so I picked
these people out because I have an
intuition that they have something to
teach me guys one of those people and I
am so so so glad that the universe
brought me a guy because not only is he
someone who is so worthy of me giving
teacherly authority he's also a brother
and he is fun and funny and light and
this whole look at your shadow thing
doesn't have to be as dark and heavy as
I once imagined you can check out guys
work at the circling Institute he's
trained thousands of people to do this
he's facilitated thousands of these
what would I say thousands of these
circles and we had just a fucking rad
time guy I love you so much thank you so
much for your time and your insight if
you guys like this conversation consider
supporting this show as you can hear in
the episode there's a little bit of a
that's because my microphone is breaking
computer broke last week microphone this
week so if you got a big pile of money
that you don't know what to do with go
ahead and send it over PayPal dot me
slash area in the air I've been
searching for those things on Craigslist
but haven't come up with anything so
without further ado here's a little bit
of beep bop to nitch I play music on
this channel to try to get you out of
whatever headspace you're in before and
kind of it's like almost a way to try to
guide you towards a certain kind of
headspace as we enter these
conversations
wah-wah-wah-wah do you need me or do you
need you need you this is the twilight
zone a little bit longer intro today
than usual
something about thinking about guys
episode yes Tiffany has given me
permission in my mind to just give a
little bit of a ramble here this morning
so
love you guys hope you enjoy this talk
with guide check out his work he's
really such a G and his name starts with
G so it's really fitting it just works
okay here we go
[Music]
adrenaline philosophy and speech ya
podcast mm-hmm that makes sense yeah
it's a good it's a really good honestly
man it's like been super helpful it's
been so therapeutic like to talk to
people like Zach Stein yeah talk to
people like Terry Patton yeah like these
are like it's pretty say gee these are
pretty say gee wise people right right
yeah I mean that you know cop I really I
really get what you're talking about
I act a lot of what I do is look at is
is looking at what happens like when we
talk to each other or what could happen
right what doesn't often happen what
could happen in conversation but when
you talk to somebody with like a really
big mind right are really connected to
some some they see something on the
horizon and I everyone else sees like to
engage in dialogue with them as to is to
kind of in some sense is to become
someone who could see that - right like
that's one of us it is there is long
there's such a sense of like impostor
syndrome that I have they're like
somehow like Zach and I do ninety
minutes is like super Jam like not just
like download from him but like a super
jam or like whoa how did that how does
that happen
exactly exactly I told Peter I'm like
I'm riding a huge wave of imposter
syndrome through this whole thing and it
yep and I like to do backflips so I do
the backflip on the wave and I just ride
it here we go sweet
so eat what has been like what has been
the impact for you on like of as evil
opened up to more more signal from other
people having this conversation what
like what's been just like when you're
walking around with your wife or when
you're like going out in the world like
what's the in what way does if it does
do these conversations kind of live in
you hmm I love that question honestly it
on one hand it helps so much just by
being able to understand things from
more perspectives and more nuanced
perspectives and more integral and meta
theoretical perspectives and to be able
to like remove myself and my attachments
from the whole picture that we are
theorizing that we are learning about
that we're talking about and that's
really really helpful yeah but on the
other hand it doesn't really mitigate
the sense of like holy shit people need
to like hear this people need to like
learn this people need to like like oh
man like we're headed towards the cliff
it's great to understand the cliff more
it's great to like understand how fast
we're going it's great to understand you
know like all the different reasons why
all this shit is like you know real and
but I don't know and there's also a
sense of there's also a sense of like
and I feel like grateful and I feel
lucky to like be in conversation like
Terry Patton was like oh let's hear your
story and then I told him basically like
my story and he's like oh yeah I love
you here's my wing and you're gonna come
right under it buddy you just come on
right under the shade of my wing I was
like wow huh so like there's I feel
really super grateful and like
to even have the conversations and it
honestly this experience this this
experience where I somehow interact with
someone's work or them online typically
through the stoah or through rebel
wisdom or through writing or articles on
medium and I email them and they have no
idea who I am and I'm like hey meet me
in a zoom meeting at this time and we
meet and we sit here for an hour and we
jam and we like connect with people that
are essentially strangers but
inspirational through a network and it's
like like that experience is just like
fucking gold man that is just gold and
I've had so much fun just like it's
crazy how deep we can go in an hour from
never meeting before right it's crazy
how far we can go and how deep we can go
and honestly like I have been like
lifting really really heavy weights with
my truthfulness muscle and especially on
the podcast like yesterday I had a big
talk with Greg and Rica's and like I
just like I told him all the ways I was
feeling and all the things I was scared
about and man that guy is just a G and
he like walk me through his like
clinical thing that he's developed over
the last two decades and so yeah it's
been it's been really therapeutic you
know cuz fuck man the world is crazy
right now the world is just crazy and
it's like the news cycle especially in
the last week the news cycle has really
come back into play in a major major way
it was like the first week of Kovan when
everything was shut down it was like
news cycle heavy and then everyone kind
of got used to it and we're like we're
kind of like getting into this thing we
were like we were managing it in a
different way and then the news cycle
came back in and it really was like hey
here's another dose of it's like almost
like intravenous
injection of adrenaline and our limbic
systems are hijacked we're all hijacked
from our from blackout Tuesday hijacked
us yeah yeah then we're like fuck we're
a bunch of white guys who never owned a
slave and who have black friends but
fuck it this whole collective trauma of
humanity for the last 4,000 years of the
history of slavery and American history
and civil rights and everything we we
have to deal with that like we that is
our trauma to heal now right which is an
interesting question you know the
question I asked my friend last night
just shooting the shit was you know it
was a month ago that I was like I would
have told you that we are all struggling
to deal with our own traumas
individually from our childhoods from
our adolescence from the first
girlfriend that dumped us from the from
our older brothers who tried to ditch us
from all the ways that we had to fight
in cloth as a school system and bullshit
and blah blah blah right we're all still
struggling mostly we don't want to do
that work mostly we want to get on with
our fucking lives and not stop being
mired in the mud and the muck of our
subconcious right and now it's like it's
almost like the media has given us this
incredibly large collective
consciousness wound the biggest one one
of the biggest ones in humanity slavery
racism prejudice hatred violence this is
the biggest this is the deepest biggest
oldest human wound right and they're
like hey you broken Millennials who are
trying to figure it out yeah this is on
you and there was enough of an algorithm
behind that that it shipped so many
people in the thing and oh shit oh it is
my thing I have to do this and people
have a panic attacks left and right
because of that message people are
having panic attacks left and fucking
right because of that
message so the question is what portion
of the human collective wound the
scourge of slavery the scourge of of
governance the scourge of violence and
control what part of that is guys what
part of that is mine
and what the fuck do you do with that
because yesterday we talked with Greg
Enrique's I I asked him I had this
intuition that there were ways that
racism and trauma and violence could be
transferred intergenerationally
subconsciously biologically without
words without mumbling the n-word under
your breath there would be ways that
these kinds of whether it's the shame of
owning slaves or the oppression or the
violence all of these traumas and he
told me like yeah there's this has been
studied over and over and over and over
like like especially in world war ii the
Polish woman who got pregnant in a
famine her child had metabolic issues
his her child's child had metabolic
issues her child's child's child had
metabolic issues after you know three
generations of not being in a famine
they're still biologically fucked up
from this trauma that's passed down not
even verbally right like they stopped
talking about grandma's stays in the
famine a long time ago but these are
things and literally like there are a
lot of different ways to think about
this and like the mythopoetic way of
understanding it has just like the human
wound that we still haven't like quite
we haven't quite cried that out yet I
think is uh it's a salient thing and I
mean we could look at that from a number
of different angles of whether that's
you know some kind of biochemical thing
that's happening because it certainly is
there's no way that you have that your
the african-americans are in a lineage
that for hundreds of years was violently
oppressed that has a profound effect on
the way
cognition develops the way your social
skills develop the way your limbic
system develops how your whole brain is
just like man from a human development
like from a childhood development
perspective 400 years of abject violence
and oppression is like I just can't
imagine what that does to a line of
people and I'm also deeply curious about
what 400 years like I like imagining
that I somehow am lineage from hundreds
of years ago slave owners like I have to
imagine that owning slaves is as
poisonous to our consciousness as being
a slave and I think that what we're
seeing and the you know the white
culture right now is this guilt this
like there's a rising up of this like
shame and this guilt from all of this
and we don't know how to deal with it we
don't know how to like we don't know how
to say sorry in a meaningful enough away
we're not sure what part of it is ours
right well I'm not sure what part of it
is mine like I have been born and raised
in Central Oregon like we read nicly
homogenous like with about 92% certainty
here you know there's like probably
seven-and-a-half Mexicans and a half a
black guy for every hundred white guys
around here right right
things are different in Alameda but I'm
sure you have lots of black friends and
aren't a racist yourself so is it fair
to say that there's something going on
where there's there's a elicitation of a
response or a call to do something or
heal something and being guilty of
something we
no clear what or where or how to act on
that sense of urgency
absolutely it's such a that's that's
yeah I think that's the I think that's
the heart of it that's the heart of the
problem right now is that I think that's
the heart of the problem right there is
that it's like this the sense that the
felt sense for me is like this anxiety
it's this panic it's this hair on fire
chicken with its head chopped off
directionless and it's also like
eggshells everywhere it's really scary
it's really scary it's like I'm like hey
like I want to be sensitive of this
right like the like bringing my
emotional awareness to the experience of
racism on top of the wounds of growing
up public school adolescence friendship
figuring out my body figuring out my
hormones figuring out my sax figuring it
like being a human is fucking
complicated let alone stacking on the
skete color of your skin and the color
of other guy's skins and they're
prejudiced that their grandpa mumbled
nigger under his breath and so now
you're just like a oh man I can't even
imagine right I can't even imagine
totally so what basically kind of like
it like I think what you think what
you're saying is at least the image I'm
getting what I'm noticing is as you're
talking the image it's forming into me
is this enormous incomprehensible
complexity uh-huh with a sit like a
sense of I need to do something about
that no-go yeah like yeah like seriously
seriously yeah it's so like orgasmic
constipation right it's like no kidding
right I know it's wrong I shouldn't oh
yeah
it sounds like a bad mushroom trip that
just never ends one wah-wah-wah-wah yeah
yeah about this is just it's kind of
like a first of all I mean my experience
with this is just I have just have find
myself having a real deep respect for
probably not fully understanding to what
degree I am a ant on top of an elephant
that is even wrong about not knowing
that it isn't an elephant it's on right
there's a there's a embeddedness that
were thrown into right that by
definition is so like you can be aware
of that we don't know though we don't
know what's happening right but that
awareness kind of in a certain sense we
can be aware of how much we don't know
it's really more like it seems like that
that that which is the case right
there's something about social media and
I think we're I think it's so new we
have no idea what what what exactly what
we're looking at with social media right
in all of the information but I think it
has this weird sense of where it takes
all that complexity it makes it super
salient in an object that you can't act
on and so like it's and so there's this
kind of weird sense where where you get
all of these signals like urgency
urgency something's wrong right like but
on these metal levels so and then all of
your signals want to go up but then
you're looking at a screen and then then
you're in this world of like opinions
and language and information and it's a
I have a feeling that the anxiety maybe
the anxiety is less to do with under an
understanding of how bad or good or
weird it is than it is about that right
yeah what the fuck do we do now
and like what it's like on some level
it's like well how do we know there is a
fuck to do now based on what what is
that
referencing right and then you look at
like well kinda we're swimming in
information without a direct encounter
in a certain sense right so it's like
we're having all these things on a very
meta level that are signalling emergency
but my embodied sense it activates the
sense of like wanting to do something
right or being guilty for something or
it activates your consciousness but
there's not there but there's no
environment directly to then act on yeah
so it's kind of a strange situation I
mean like fuck I mean I'm looking at all
this stuff I mean I I get I get there's
racism involved I mean but is the
response of what all the stuff I'm
hearing is it about racism or is it
about something else yeah what exactly
are Pete like it what I don't know like
I don't know if anybody quite knows
right it's so it's so complicated yeah
and the nefarious agendas of all the
possible actors who are poking the you
know the American system when it's very
fragile like it's a fragile system it's
very fragile it's on the knife's edge of
just blowing up like I have friends
further south in California than you and
they're telling me that they're seeing
these pallets of bricks being delivered
to places where protests are planned
yeah and I'm like oh my god that's like
inciting violence and citing the the
shift in citing the shift from protest
to riot the the the shift from protest
to looting
hmm yeah there's all kinds of there's
all kinds of things that I can't know
that I'm so so skeptical of I'm so
skeptical of and I know in general that
trying to solve racism with Facebook is
like trying to cook dinner over a crayon
drawing of a fire yeah
and that's a bit so that that right
there is a world we've never been in
before or it's only been there for 15
years right like in what's strange about
that world is how much it just
disappears like it's taking something
for us to our like to lift it up into
and to talk about it and reveal it
because we're there's something about
technology that seems to the
characteristic of it is it these
miraculous things like the internet and
every bill the entire being able to have
a thought and like directly transmitted
to the entire world in a second and your
finger actually on your watch right only
happened I don't know
years ago yeah and it's we end up living
inside of it in it Fasching in us and it
disappearing into the background right
so I think it's like I think it's more
there's there's so much going on right
now that we have no idea how to
completely understanding it's actually a
little own sea right absolutely dude I I
think that we are in uncharted waters
and it's it's it's really it's almost
funny I want to say funny it's
interesting it's scary but it's also
funny how quickly we get used to shit
because cell phone thing the social
media thing it's like it's like you know
I think our hair might not be on fire
for we have no idea what we're doing to
our minds with social media we don't
know what we're doing to our minds with
with cell phone
that have social media on them available
to us all the time the other day I'm
riding my bike home and I ride by this
like construction site there's this
beautiful home being built and there's
like this big pile of dirt and in the
pile of dirt is standing like a 13 12 13
year old boy he's got a shovel it's
stuck in the ground he's holding on to
it with one hand the other hand he's
holding his cell phone and he's just
scrolling his look on his face is just
blank when I was his age and a little
bit younger my father built a custom
home that we lived in and I had to do
all kinds of work on the house back
filling the foundation just like this
kid was supposed to be doing right and I
would get so bored I would totally avoid
my work I would totally everything but
shovel but I didn't have a fucking cell
phone to scroll on I definitely didn't
have any kind of social connection I
would toss rocks up into the air and hit
him with the shovel like a baseball bat
we would throw dirt clods at each other
ad infinitum you know until my front
tooth was knocked out and my brother had
a black eye right and that's like so wow
is that this that like right there like
and the age development like like seeing
my mother and stepfather scrolling way
more than they should on Facebook and
I'm like holy shit like they're old but
like that's having a profound effect on
them and I think back you know I think
to the kid to the kids who are so much
more pliable so much more malleable and
who inherently are in a stage of
development that that desires and
requires so much more social connection
holy fuck I feel like I'm I'm still
trying to shed the fucking wounds of my
own needs for social connection my own
you know the times that I was ditched by
my brother my older brother and his
friend
because I wanted to be I wanted to be
cool I wanted to be accepted in their
group and I wasn't or the times in just
middle school in high school where he's
just the turmoil of the the Lord of the
Flies situation that his American public
school is like man I can't imagine what
cell phones and social media are doing
to us oh my god my I mean I did three
years with the flip phone because at
some point my cell phone came out of my
pocket on its own accord and looked at
my face
so many times that I was just like why
are you looking at me why do I have this
app open why do I have social media open
right now I was like I can't do this I
mean I'm I'm not responsible enough
right right well you know to give this a
person perspective is it you know think
about it like okay so what one like a
person that's just been I'd been
grappling with for like total for 20
years
philosopher Martin Heidegger and I'm I'm
only in the last few years really
starting to understand what his pretty
prophetic understanding of the age of
technology we would call it right that
what what what makes you know it in you
can't really summer
Heidegger but like you know basically he
his big thing was like philosophy in
some way was predicated on the Western
understanding of the cut of the of the
notion of being right the being of
beings and he's like this is the one
culture that where we started to
actually understand or have an
understanding of the being in which
unites all particular beings and it's
like you could say it's like almost like
understanding an understanding of the
info like the the the horizon of
inexhaustible intelligibility right that
upon which by virtue of which anything
is intelligent as anything at all right
and so Heidegger notice that the
as a there is a movement or his
historicity to that understanding
through the West right and of course you
know the the the deepest level of
context your your understanding of that
kind of your orientation of that context
is going to be the orientation of
everything within that context right so
if it changes right everything changes
and our embodiment and our in early
experience in our pre reflective sense
of what anything is and its significance
or lack of significance and if you look
at history you know the West like really
was one of the only cultures that has
this movement of progress right all
other cultures there they were banking
on staying the same as long as possible
from fucking thousands of years right
like the same structures and like
cyclical time and all this stuff but you
hit the West and something dramatically
different happens and so he's a lot of
his philosophy was trying to oh this a
date you could say feel into the that
understanding of being and it's gonna be
the thing that's most concealed to us
it'll because it hides itself in its
obvious nacelle technology right he
would say is you know at some point
there was we understood being the being
of beings as subjects and objects
anything that was anything right was
predicated on this notion of that if it
was something it was a subject and
object right started to car right and it
was the first to name it and Kant all
that kind of stuff right and then into
the Industrial Revolution right it
really kind of like you could see the
movement of that understanding right
being like in the Industrial Revolution
where all of a sudden we have machines
in factories where it's like the subject
is starting to overcome the dominance of
the object right and at some point I
don't know exactly when this transition
was but each he comes along and he
speaks the understanding of being right
of where he says it's like the anta
theology or the innermost understanding
the gods IV who come together and you
would say that it's the that the the the
innermost was the absurdum of the will
to power which means just kind of this
it's kind of like meaningless surging up
of energy right if you will like this is
the whole nietzsche thing and then the
the the the Pheo straight the the
theological or the God's eye view was
the eternal return of the same swelling
up of of will and then the the endless
order ordering a repetition of that will
and he says that was the beginning of
the technological age right and that's
the one that were inside of and so if we
kind of look at this done it more of a
grunt like a less of an abstract level
and you look at like well how did is it
how is that playing out right so like if
you just look at our relationship to our
bodies right before the Industrial
Revolution right when you life was so
fucking embodied and required so much of
your body right that like life itself
had your body in some sense disappear
right into your life and then and then
machines kind of came along and the
Industrial Revolution and all of a
sudden maybe it began to like bring the
world into a small circle in front of
you and in that moment right we no
longer had to move as much all of a
sudden we realize there's this thing
called we started to add these notions
called physical fitness right like our
body started to come into viewers or in
an object given that given that embedded
understanding right and so all of a
sudden people realize well like if you
don't move you get fat
oh there's a thing called your body and
fitness in this very kind of world right
and then now check that out then then
how did we start to deal with it and
then you started to realize like oh
fitness all
well how do we deal with that well will
will create rooms right and then will
will create rooms that concentrate
gravity and then you'll get a membership
to that room and then you'll go in right
and then you'll you'll make a
concentrated room so that you make it
hard for a shorter amount of time such
that you exercise this body and then do
right radical shift and the
understanding of being a body and having
a body right and that's so built into
the intelligibility of the of the
everyone right everyone knows now I
should exercise everyone knows now I
have this health that I should butter
everyone knows now it's like you go down
to you know 500 years ago like he asked
him about their fitness or their health
it's like all all you probably hear
about is like a story about them in in
in the farm
it's like indistinguishable from the
world right so it's so there's this that
but I think now there's another version
of that happening in relationship right
so like it's not even been at all like
25 years ago was the first answering
machine and I think that that's a
starting point of a major thing a major
shift in relationship and communication
and and interaction where with the
answering machine was I think the first
time where if I before before that if I
had an idea or wanted to exchange
information it I least had to call you I
always had to go it had this exchange
through this embodied verbal anything
about what it is to have a conversation
with somebody it's like it's filled with
ambiguity it's filled with all kinds of
social practices it's filled with the
possibility of shame right like you
could say something to me they can
reveal something about me that can like
put me into a trauma that I need therapy
for 10 years like that's all or you
could say something mean it'll enlighten
me right and make me a girl roofer
twenty years right that all that's
possible in this bizarre thing called
intersubjectivity now the answering
machine was the very beginning where
somebody could actually exchange
information without going through that
nervous system awkward identity forming
courtroom right of justification called
social interaction and if you think
about how we all know were us how I know
this is my face and I have a name and
like like on so many different levels I
come to be via through and in
articulation of that sociality right
like I walk around all day talking to
people in my head responding to what
this person thinks or like in ways that
I can't even comprehend it's okey right
what does it mean right to then you know
there's answering machines and then
there's texting and then there's
Facebook but what's the what's the
what's the experience with the answering
machine that you're referring to it's
that you can communicate or like
transmit information without actually
having a dialogue yes I can like I can
receive a communication and be a
spectator of that reception versus being
and involved cuz like in a conversation
huh you don't even know what you're
gonna say you find out what you're gonna
say is much as the other person does
right like the moment I articulate a
thought it's indistinguishable from the
understanding that you're having of it I
cannot known without being know there's
a constant and there's a there's an
aliveness that's so native to us that is
so deep in our nervous system our
nervous systems are designed to have
that that's what kind of makes us us and
so like if you think about it what
happens just like with you know the
analogy that I'm kind of highlighting
with our bodies
right where there's a division between
my life and my my needing to respond and
bodily to it there's now a division that
transforms everything about the body
including what the body is right so now
if you look at the level of like
sociality in relationship right when you
start to remove right and you put this
word now it's an option where it never
was an option what is that what does
that mean and I think the thing about it
is that because I mean at Marshall
McLuhan saw this like really clearly
that like whenever there's a big change
in communication it changes everything
right like the from oral culture to
alpha Braddock literature and like the
world is completely different after that
right like that it's like it fashions us
so I'm kind of like you know it's truly
strange I and so there's this kind of if
we look at that there's this radical
revolution if you will or shift right
and how we understand ourselves that
disappears so quickly right it
disappears so quickly what are you
getting easier as dear you're moving my
humble musings on I love your musings
making my way I love your musings I
think this is a I love the analogy
between our bodies that in that our
lives used to be embodied that there was
our bodies didn't even exist because
they were just so integral in our
existence and now we just everything is
so easy in a way that like the grocery
store and the light switch and the
heater are just all automatic and set to
thermostats and powered by the grid yeah
yeah and we used to do those things
with our bodies and to even think about
my grandmother she died in November he
was 84 years old she was the rodeo queen
the state barrel racing record holder
she was the daughter of homesteaders
cattle ranchers and to think about how
those like my great-grandparents I knew
them till I was 16 right they'd I don't
know 16 they lived really long lives to
think about their idea of their health
elf the fuck is health yeah brand we
brand the cattle you wake up and we
drink we drink coffee and we eat bacon
and you know like but in never yeah
you're Betty never was an object of
significance in distinguished
indistinguishable from the world in
which you were embedded it right so it's
like oh it's like oh yeah a breakdown at
health was more like I can't move the
cattle anymore what are we gonna do it's
like and usually there's a tradition of
like oh that's because y-you have sons
the end there uh-huh
like that's a real Surat achill shift in
going to look at your your body as an
object in which you optimize and tend to
write like even me IV I'm talking about
all stuff like it and I I love the whole
idea of like hacking your biology like
you like but this is quality of like
wits with technology versus like
mechanician and industry had this sense
of you know if you look at the
difference between like a windmill a
windmill is a technology but it's at a
completely different level because it's
like you you you create this windmill
and it and it and it access the wind
right and utilizes the wind to to rotate
but it but it leaves the wind as it is
right like it's attune to the wind in
such a way versus something like nuclear
energy which literally
like breaks atoms and extracts energy
out this mo notion of extracting
something out optimizing something is
the radical difference that is it's
here's the thing it's not that we do
that it's not the objects of technology
it's not that we have technology I mean
what Heidegger was pointing into him
what I'm trying to kind of reveal in the
conversation to myself and continually
look at is because it disappears so
quick is that work we're now the
standing reserve we're now we now see
ourselves as having a body to optimize
like my I look at my brain like oh yeah
I get these supplements in these things
and he do these running I'm gonna just
suck the most out of the most memory out
of this fucking thing I'm gonna tweak it
here and like that's it like the
intelligent that the Intel intelligent
intelligibility that by virtue of which
grants that is being a good thing to do
right that's the understanding of being
in the background that means to us yeah
yeah it's like you're like you're like a
rice burner mod in your Honda Civic
you're newly newly licensed driver
you're gonna get as much horsepower out
of this sixty four horsepower two
seconds faster than before yeah that is
not because you're faster phone because
you do see there's a momentum to it
bring it more there's more of a sense of
it has us right than us having it that's
scary that's scary and the momentum is
if you can zoom out enough to see the
speed at which this really heavy object
is moving is scary
but there was one thing that came up for
me there about the windmill analogy that
I
actually think that the windmill leaves
the wind as it is from our ability to
understand it it leaves it as it is but
there's no doubt that there's an
exchange of force right and we know that
the laws of physics say that we are
slowing down the wind ever so slightly
with those windmills just like the
ground has dragged right this is an
aerodynamics and you're well it's
interesting like so here here's what I
mean one of the things you can think
about this is where were we talking
about like our way of making sense of
the world is given by a horizon of
intelligibility right of like how things
show up for us in the way they do it's
not like how we can even send them yeah
yeah the way that the agent arena
relationship first we find ourselves in
right that agent arena relationship that
people 500 years ago found themselves in
where it was like the salience of it
what showed up what it was was
completely different right on some level
and so all their actions was in response
to that showing right and they weren't
aware of it as much as you and I weren't
aware of it that's how it works it's
just it's in the the you could say it's
in the primordial risk immediate
responsiveness of how the world shows up
as anything at all and that as structure
of being right the being of being right
like things things show up ads this or
as that and then I have thoughts about
them right that ad structure so I you
know if you think about it like like for
the person like when the person building
the windmill thought of the wind right
in a certain sense
you really did have to relate to the
wind as the wind right it was what it
does it like did its own thing there was
something beyond that person that he
could come into relationship with and
attuned to it in such a way that they
could like everything about it was a in
attuned into the wind being the wind
right and that's why windmills are
beautiful right there's a beauty of the
tune it to a craftsmanship that was
attune to the being of the wind but like
I think now we think of the wind and we
picture a power plant right or we
picture a resource which we can optimize
right what the high degree would say
it's like we no longer when we picture
the Rhine we don't see a gathering River
that unites two countries or whatever
right and the people gather around
instead we see a power plant right so
things show up for us as a standing
reserve right awaiting our utilization
in the in extraction for our own purpose
and you can see that filtered all the
way down into people like oh yeah like
what's your network right how many
people are in your network right like
like how can you optimize your network
how many friends do you have like
there's a quality where even people show
up for us like that so I think about
like okay so so tie this bet I'm curious
how this ties to social media or like
how social media and how our phones how
this technology is showing up how our
scene and how its emerging yeah exactly
exactly so here's here's one of the
things about again it's just really it's
it's difficult not enough to even see it
right let alone to know what to do about
it right and that's some of that's some
of the irritation that comes up for me
or some of the some of the like the way
people are responding oftentimes
I mean and Nora Bateson talks about this
a lot too and I and I really appreciate
what the what she's highlighting in this
and she's like you know the in a system
a major change in a system right where
does it take place it takes place in the
in the smallest relation right where
does the major system like change happen
it it changes in the smallest integrity
right of the of the me and you having
this conversation as we're walking down
the street right that's where that
system change happens right and so this
kind of way of looking at the world's
problems as in in kind of
conceptualizing and as a problem which
turns it into an object that we can
solve
he was like part of the problem right so
I think where I've kind of come down to
like for myself in my experiences
because one of the things I do is is is
I'm a co-founder of the practice called
circling circling method which is
something that emerged between some
friends of mine and I that
it glowed to us in a particular way and
we it caught our attention we started
moving towards it and wonder what it's
evolved to be right is it a day you
could say is a inner subject of yoga
right which is so telling of our times
like just like we needed gyms once the
Industrial Revolution came up to relate
to our bodies I think it's telling of
our time that something like circling is
becoming so popular because what
circling is is basically looking at what
is it right what are the things the
underlying components that that underlie
all profound conversations by all
moments of deep intimacy where like
there's something about the interaction
is innately nourishing to our humanity
to our senses to our sovereignty right
like what if we if we looked at those
conversations and we looked at like okay
what are the the come from what are the
environments what are the understandings
what's the way of being that that seem
to seem to invite that garden to grow
circling is like a yoga or making that
in asanas that people go in and practice
sitting in and so I think that's one
response to all this is is that there's
one of the places where being in it's
mystery right in its humaneness can
still reach us it's through
intersubjectivity and i think that's
what you're talking about like how when
you were referring to having these
conversations look these really amazing
people right like it wasn't like what
I'm hearing what I heard in that is it
wasn't like you were you've had these
isolated interactions with people that
you look back on and go that was really
neat there's something about the
interaction that affects how I see right
there's something about the dialogues
and the movements of dialogue so what it
takes to understand what Terry Patten is
talking about right like in what you
feel and then all of the subtle like
social things that are going on in the
movement of the dialogue and all the
mimicry and the horizons that open up
that when we walk away you look at you
know the way that you kiss your wife at
bed at night is somehow more available
in a new way right
these ways in which we look he can be
with another another really sink in
together into deep conversation into
deep intimacy I think is is is something
that cannot be in framed or cannot be
optimized right it's one of the realms
that it's still a connection to the
mister being is still available
so that's one of the that's one of the
places I've really brought my attention
and and is creating ways in which that
can be for they'll build more people I
love that and this is why I called guy
this is why I called I wanted to hear
all about this I have had a conversation
with Sara Ness you know Sara's you
started authentic relating yeah and
there have been ways in which
interactions that have a deep intimacy
and a raw truthfulness have like changed
my life and how I see things right I
think that there's a lot of people I
think most people have had that
experience where there's like some kind
of either conversation or like even
sometimes it's moments in tragedy
honestly that people are just so present
and real and vulnerable that there's
like there's like a real there's like a
real connection the shit kind of falls
away so I really like I don't know what
circling is exactly like I kind of I
kind of know all right I guess I have
any I have an idea
I have an idea but I really like like
one of the things I talked to Greg and
Rica is about yesterday was that I
actually want my all of my relationships
to be more therapeutic and I want my
interactions like I want to be
therapeutic for people I'm I
historically I am inspiring
I am invigorating I am challenging I am
motivating I'm not that therapeutic I'm
not that I'm not that nourishing I'm I'm
invigorating and enlivening well I'm not
that nourishing and well I could tell
you I can tell you moments where I felt
really nourish being with you thank you
yeah
I would love to hear that it was like
monk there are moments where you were
I felt I felt you being impacted in a
direct way in the conversation that that
had me kind of sink deeper into what I
was thinking and understanding right and
in that listening there was a way where
there was a real natural sense of flow
that I felt with you and just the kind
of feeling of your fairness in the
conversation was like us I can open this
it I think just had me go into a flow
state with you and then I kind of as I
was sitting back listening to you I was
actually thinking to myself oh yeah
really full and grateful and nourished
hmm thank you that's a really nice
reflection and I think there's a couple
things that I feel like you're you're
putting your finger really close to what
I think is kind of at the heart of some
of these things and one of them is being
open being up for grabs as Limburg calls
it being up for grabs I love this idea
of being up for grabs because I come
into this conversation with you having
credence that you are a thinker and that
you have ideas and that I am up for
grabs I am willing to be seduced by
ideas the best ones the good ones the
right ones right and so I I come into
this conversation looking for more
perspective looking for more nuance
looking to be changed looking for
transformation and for healing on my own
part yeah so that I come to this
conversation with that and and I think
that there's a and I would love to hear
from you because obviously as a Europe
founder and longtime practitioner of
this kind of stuff there's a new
friendship that I have with a younger
man and he's incredibly useful to a
fault like it's it's home it seems like
it comes from guilt and it's like
something that I so want to kind of
shine some light on and there's a
closeness to his verbal interactions
that is absolutely callous to me that is
irritating that is like like he's just
like he's not up for grabs
he's not up for grabs and it drives me
crazy
because I see just an enormous potential
I just love the kids so much and I just
don't want him to give away his life to
fill this this bottomless pit of having
to please people and having to like be
useful and so I care about him yeah I do
like in fact your frustration and his
close it nests right it is his only
presupposes that you really see
potential and a possibility for him and
with his life thus it's painful to see
anything in the way of that absolutely
and this is what I mean when historic I
say that historically I'm motivating
historically I'm in invigorating and I'm
inspiring
I like there's a part of me that is
stick and not carrot would you say that
again it's a part of me there's what
stick and not carrot
a stick and not carrot yeah there's a
part of me that just like wants to slap
him on the ass so hard that it hurts
enough that he goes hey hey oh whoa
maybe I yeah maybe you're right maybe
this carrot isn't fucking good
maybe I should live my own life maybe I
should not worry about money in the way
that I do maybe I should what do I want
to do with my life what is the most
pleasant way for me to exist what is the
most fulfilling way for me to exist hmm
I think when he was the victim of a deep
neglected as a child a deep neglect well
I think so I guess what I'm what I'm
pointing at what I'm curious about what
is I think like the thread that I'm on
here is like the transformational power
of openness hmm yeah transformational
power of openness and what like I almost
need from you like a pretty morning show
I need a morning show introduction into
what circling is and I feel like the
thread that I'm on is the
transformational power of openness and
what and how certainly news is that
because I just I have this intuition
that it does yeah totally well if we
look at like soap foster first of all I
really I just want to say I just really
feel in a visceral way because you were
talking about him I just feel how much
you're for him right like everything
everything even even you're like
irritation with him and one of these all
that just seems what shines through to
me is that you fucking to care about
right like to the degree that you've
you're hit him being free to to him
being free for his possibilities to be
right or of the order of of your concern
here we are having this conversation
isn't really barely know and you're
bringing it up like New York you're
holding him right first of all
is that just that having that like
having you in his life when he isn't
even thinking about you and he's not
around that you're talking about him and
you're considering him and you're living
with him you have him in your concern
that in itself I just want to commend
thank you and I think that the I I want
to learn from you as to how I take that
impulse yeah and I don't spill it on the
floor
I totally you know yeah well I tell you
why from somebody who spilled down in
the floor a bunch of time I get that
concerned right you're like no no I'm
not the guy that doesn't spill it I'm
the guy with the mop sorry sorry yeah
well you know here's the thing if we
look at like well what is being open
with him an inviting openness mean in
this case right like so now to invite
openness is also a framework that I want
to squeeze out of you totally well it's
it's a it here's the thing about it is
that like you see a possibility for him
and when you look at the way that he is
in certain cases you see that that
possibility diminished right and then
what ends up happening is you care about
him I would imagine you you just want to
show him that possibility and have a
glow for him because that if you could
really get it right then then he would
like be able to see that like oh he
needs to open up or whatever it is the
qualities or virtues that one would
right have if they saw the thing that
you see right so I think the thing about
it is that like so what this from a
circling perspective there's a thing
there's a there's a stage encircling so
so circling basically was something we
discovered and then we started paying
attention to it and then we it's it's
informed us over the years we're able to
start to articulate it started to reveal
itself and
different facets and distinctions so
circling you know out of that inquiry
basically has what I call seven stages
of circling and the in the the first one
is sovereignty right
Who am I right what do I feel what do I
want
where am I located right and then once I
I'm here then then I could go who are
you and and so the second stage is the
Explorer I think what we're talking
about is the Explorer stage here which
is and it's predicated on this
understanding that that everything that
we do everything a human being does
always makes sense
and it makes sense because everything
that they're doing like with their
behavior with their responses with their
emotions with their thoughts it's always
in the context of their world like
there's no self that then is in the
world no their self world there's age of
dureena it arises at one so that he's
closing this right you could say if you
get in there if you could start to
understand what is it that he what is it
what is how his life showing up for him
such that being closed what you're
calling enclosed is a completely
intelligent response right like ii maybe
you find out you go in there you maybe
find out it's like like oh yeah I just
noticed when I said hi do you you you
you know you just you know you went stir
or something like that it goes it like
what one way to do that is going like
you shouldn't do that like fuck I Love
You Man that's one way of doing it but
another way of getting is world is more
like that when Singh what oh is that a
response to you like what how does that
make sense like I trust that there's an
intelligibility in there but I want to
be able to get in your position so that
I can really crock the way this this
what's sailing it for you
and if I can understand what's salient
for you then all of a sudden I can
articulate back to you why it makes
sense that of course you would fuck
what's right of course you know well
what's interesting about that is that
that kind of getting someone's world is
usually rare but it's interesting other
thing I've experienced this over and
over and over and over and over again is
people people say this thing about
circling I have this experience of
circling and where they'll say something
like whoa I feel deeply seen right what
they're saying right in some sense is
that phrase if you take it literally
doesn't it it's really strange because
like well why like well I'm me so you
see me okay great
I saw me that's not what we're talking
about like it's like when when what
they're saying is like when I have the
experience of being deeply seen it means
that like oh how I make sense to the
world right is more of like revealed to
me right in my sense of validity as as a
being gray my sense of deep validity
right as a being is intelligible enough
such that you can articulate it back to
me there's this kind of love of pouring
forth of affinity that comes out right
well what's interesting is that ends up
being very transformational in how they
see because they've never seen their own
see right like it's like you know if you
asked me to describe everything I see
most likely I wouldn't just arrive the
rooms of my classes because they see
with them so like getting someone's
world is like in getting them we get
your world in other words we get the
structures upon which you make sense of
everything right and how why things show
up as they do and how it just totally
makes sense that they're contractor
you're contracted in this way or you're
spawning this way but what's interesting
is that when you see your own seeing
you're no longer seeing with it you're
seeing it which starts to breathe that
it starts to invite a new a new
intelligibility and a higher level of
city into you're seeing right and so and
then when I was up happening is that
then then for you it's like with him you
can start to when he does that uh or
whatever he does that shows up as his
contraction did ye all of a sudden that
moment is gonna transform for you too
because all of a sudden it's not gonna
be just this irritating thing that's
getting in his way
oh there's a way he's seeing it and you
can join him in his world and get
curious about it so what is this I love
that I think that's foundational and
that's really like I feel like there's
such a personal how would I say there's
like we have such a propensity for all
of our interactions to be personal in a
way like that every response that his
wince is about me right that's our
that's our first propensity which it
spoils the the nourishment it spoils the
therapeutic opportunity to come into his
world right and to but we take it as
personal so I think that's really
important but I want to hear just like
in not abstraction what circling is what
does it look like - like how long does
it take how do we like physically what
do we do like what is what is circling
as a practice yeah totally so circling
as a prac oh just one more thing I just
felt like a salt what's that thing I was
talking about and they think actually
the virtue that you embody when you get
someone else's world that is expressed
to the other person and with each other
is is reverence to even even to go
you're you're a legitimate other you see
things you have a way of seeing things
and I like that there's that you're
beyond my conception of you right to be
up to approach somebody like that
presupposes that's kind of like the
place in which that beyond this one it's
a humble place but it's a reverent place
and I think that reverence for you and
as a being right in the respect that
comes through that is implicitly
communicated in in just the attempt to
and I would have to say that people I
bet you if you really take a look if to
the to the degree that he gets in his
own way in his life are probably the
result of not people being overly
reverent with him right so like just
that reverence in itself is a virtue
that a tooth can it can it tune in
afford so much and I think that our
society right now what we're seeing
especially with the race issues and with
all of this like the you know as Martin
Luther King says that the riots are the
language of the unheard there is like
there is this deep desire to have
reverence for our experiences for our
existence for our lives there is like
this outcry of like witnessed me like
please fucking witness me like please I
am NOT I am NOT your conception of me I
am something totally totally more
complex and bigger and deeper than that
so please PLEASE witness me I totally
see that I totally see that an end I
look at like yeah totally so if you look
at like a practice of reference I mean I
think essentially that's what circling
is if you look at it from from a
Socratic
you know platonic neo platonic
standpoint I think what circling is is
really the practice of referencing
of the virtue of having reverence and
connecting with reverence into what's
possible and beyond all of us when we
meet right so like what it off that like
what it looks like is it is that
basically it's like we set the intention
there's a group of people usually and
there's one way of doing it where we
just somebody plays the role of the
person who's who's being circled right
who who is is having everyone's
attention is on and the other people
there's usually a leader who has
training in all the stages and stuff
like that and then there's people
participating and you could say
basically what the intention is and what
we're practicing is just it's the
simplest thing in the world is we're
practicing being with what is however
when you think about it through
reverence right it's being with what is
from a place of reverence right
like inherently saying that like what is
can disclose more of itself through our
reviewing of it through our observation
of it through the way that we are with
it and so the the person who plays the
role of having the attention being
listened to right being gotten right is
isn't that part of the practice and then
the other people who are participating
and leading are enacting that in in
another way the thing about circling
though is like where a lot of things
like a more of a therapeutic nature that
work with groups kind of have that
structure to it however it's it's a very
different intention right it's it's the
intention isn't to help the person or
like or to have the person get something
or work through something or something
like that right that's actually kind of
the opposite of the intention the
intention is like no I'm gonna sit down
with you and I'm going to enjoy the
living shit out of you right I'm gonna
like just literally in a certain sense
see how deeply related I can
with myself in my experience of being
with you and then starting to notice
what we noticed and getting finding out
what's happening in your world a lot of
times it's just like one of the things
that we that we really focus on it was
circling is the practicing of just being
with the relationship that's in the room
I think a lot of the pitfalls that I
think I hear a lot of a lot of circling
kind of go down the road it's an
understandable one but it's kind of like
I think it's a pitfall which is they
they have this kind of notion of the
present moment as this animistic like in
the now the temporal now or something
right
that's not actually what being in the
moment is for you and being it's like
the moment unfolds more like we
experience music right the present beat
right it seems because to the degree
that it's anticipating the next beat and
it's like the repetition of the last and
so that present beat just actually is
just the place where those two things
interpenetrating they're transparent and
a revelation of the whole song that's
emerging so that that sense of presence
of of where we're recognizing there's
what we're talking about but were
there's also moments where we stop where
we go okay what's happening right now so
understanding that about you you
understanding that with us what's the
connection like now and they may be like
oh whoa I wasn't even noticing but I
fucking feel like you're the best person
I've ever met my life it's like this is
this affinity okay so let's like you
with that infinity and like experience
all of it and that's where it becomes
like a meditation or a yoga where it's
like you're you're really like with a
meditation you're good you're being with
all the nuances of awareness and
attention of the body and you're being
with those almost like for their own
sake right going into a deep practice
such that so that when you walk out
those capacities are free to tab their
own life in your own in your own the
world it's like that with relationship
it's a yoga of relationship in that in
that regard and so I probably like led I
don't know I number of years ago I
calculated it I think that I had led up
to that point like six thousand circles
so I think you're probably up to eight
or nine thousand and I still don't know
what's gonna happen
yeah when a circle starts I literally I
got a I'm really comfortable with the
restraints and the distinctions at the
sentence setting but that set in setting
designs for a revelation of what's most
essential about you you're such this but
it also opens up to the more nests or
the the inexhaustible the ontological
the ground of our being
right through the deeply personal
there's also people can have these
really mystical experiences around that
that are very very feet they're very
real yeah you're basically plotting a
graph that then turns into a Mandelbrot
and the further you zoom in the more
complex it gets yeah that's the thing
that really hit me in the head like a
brick
there was the delineation between an
intention of therapeutic an intention of
helpfulness an intention of usefulness
versus an intention of awareness or
being with yeah what really is and
that's like I say it hits me in the head
like a brick because there's some pain
associated with the awareness of the
times in my life that I have even just
in what we're talking about my
relationship with this young guy the
desire I have to help the desire I have
to like illuminate or enlighten or
liberate and that is something that can
I mean that's I spilled I spill the bowl
on the
lower there with that and and we that is
I think that epitomizes how we go wrong
so much and this ties back to this whole
racism thinking we're talking about this
whole I had I had this epiphany
yesterday that I was like oh my god I
needed tweet the words don't get mad get
sad like stop trying to fix it and just
fucking feel it for a second yeah we're
we're swear our hair is on fire our hair
is on fire yeah in the action of fixing
right what will fix it if we want to use
that right is only gonna be as effective
as how much we can perceive it right
it's when so one of the things I think
circling has really taught me so
attunement right with another person
attunement is this kind of quality of
where it's like this kind of non
conceptual sense in which your with thie
with the other and their fullness in a
way that you kind of like feel into the
same sound that they're in and how you
know is that you're humming with their
hum in this way right it's this
experience you don't know it you feel it
right opportunity and so you can you can
have this quality of like if I'm giving
you I'm hearing you my words can be in
direct response right what's happening
with you and it registers right away
which feeds back to me that I'm on or
I'm not on so so this kind of quality of
understanding the problem right creating
a strategy and an acting upon the
problem is another way right which is
more like feeling it right and realizing
that action is wedded to perception
more I can perceive the more visible and
invisible interrelations that I can I
can perceive in a tune with the more
implicitly my response is gonna be in
with the relationship and that feedback
loop can be there it's like uh Nora's
dad Gregory Bateson that he's considered
like the second father of cybernetics
and system thinking he said that you
know because we don't see all of the the
integrity of the intricate relations
that make up the earth because we don't
see them
we can't relate to them right and he
said and I think what he was saying that
he was highlighting like no it's not
like we're bad people it's just that we
don't see and if we saw them there's an
implicit generosity in the statement
that if we if we could see them and see
the relations right we our actions would
be in relationship to that so there's a
quality I think what I'm talking about
as we're speaking into I'm getting this
sense of just seeing your care for this
boy and just of like that your care in
itself is already there it will it will
you'll act in a to admit with him it's
not it's probably like the the way that
you can act your care you can you can
express your care is by perceiving it
more like understanding more being
surprised by him really seeing him as a
valve and it's not like that you're then
gonna have to then you'll know what to
do you'll find yourself doing it as you
that's what care is like them you're
already caring about him right I but I
think authenticity is and you could say
is the way that we the habit upon which
we take up that care right how deeply we
are in that care
[Music]
I love that idea that the reverence the
reverence of gaining the perspective of
wanting to see more is that is the
action that dad is the that's the thing
it's not like if I can see you enough
then I'll develop some kind of solution
it's like the act of seen is the thing
that's the fucking Mandelbrot it's like
you just got to keep zooming in on the
Mandelbrot yeah so right there right
there I think you just did it go on well
I just you went you took everything I
was saying it and then you basically re
articulated what you saw right like but
I would say that there's a way in which
you're there's if we look at a
tournament in this moment
like what's the achievement level
between each other would you say quite
high yeah why high yeah yeah that's what
I mean
yeah I just I'm really appreciating
you're listening and I think when you
talked about like how you show up you
show up there was a word that you use I
show up wanting to be changed on what
I'm hearing in the podcasts right with
these people what a great fuckin what a
great context to be able to listen
mm-hmm right like I'm gonna so fully
release my sensorium might care up to
what you're saying that like that in
understanding to you I am I am wanting
and willing to when I come back to
myself I will be a new person I will be
different in some way and it's
interesting that difference in the way
that you're listening to me seeing the
difference in you in the subtle and not
so
waise has me it gives me the experience
of being heard by you right it's not so
much you understanding me although you
do but like it's the sense in which the
pasta the possibilities that the
possibilities of the various
possibilities that are presencing in
your life that are you're talking about
how something is more that possibility
is more accessible to you right and in
that sense it's like seeing that shift
in you has me in some level like relaxed
like I'm like I feel deeply heard
there's an affinity with you so I just
want to acknowledge I want to thank you
for your your your ability your capacity
for listening it has me just has me just
when I think about that and I just think
about like if you like just that with
him like if he was one of your podcast
so the next time you see me just sit
down like huh just that just that
openness to him mm-hmm I'm curious as to
the role in which my own preconceived
respect or reverence right like like I I
called you because like I know you have
something to teach me and I like that's
a preconceived notion that I come into
the conversation with yep yep and so it
is enlightening to how I spill the ball
by coming into a conversation where I
have something to teach right this
closedness creates a frustration in me
because I'm like shut up and listen yeah
and when I when I come to the
conversation with no tell me more tell
me more tell me more tell me more
well it's a very different experience
for me for sure yeah yeah I think you
just really just said something really
profound a distinction that's typically
what I that's kind of what I'm referring
to when I say that historically I've
been invigorating inspiring and live in
like like have you ever been 10,000 feet
off of the ground and a thermal like
trust me there are higher states of
enlivened niss that are available to you
that you haven't yet considered yeah
yeah totally yes right and that's like
that's the part of me that gets
sponsorships that's part of me that I
when I sit down at the table with the
marketing directors at a brand they're
like holy fuck it was this guy they're
like wow like they feel it they feel it
themselves
they're like maybe our viewers will feel
it mm-hmm yeah but then I think that
that's the that's not a nourishing yeah
that's not the therapeutic part of
myself yeah yeah the invigorating and
live inning like that's one side of it
that's on the other side of complexity
though that's not on the other side of
of the therapeutics right yeah because
I feel like he had to break it down
before he build it up all right all
right and so sounds like it's like wait
I think what I'm hearing you say it's
like you're gonna you're in a dialectic
right now right you're these two things
are starting to talk to each other right
which is like oh there's this the the
therapeutic right and then there's the
inspiration the inspirational mm-hmm
like I'm really like I huh I know this
inspiration part and it works really
like well and it does really cool things
that I would do over and over and over
again it works in all these different
ways and it's like contributes and I
like that part of myself and then
there's this other side called
therapeutic that when I try to do this
at there there I mean it frustrated I
interpret it sounds like unsolicited
advice it sounds like fucking beating a
dead horse it sounds like yeah it feels
like closing this and the other person
yeah totally I
and I'm wondering right I'm wondering if
it has to do with the relationship right
because it's kind of like from a level
of like you're speaking to people that
you're not in interfacing with right and
you're you're presencing a possibility
right that their freedom engage with or
not but you're not in relationship with
them like the more enlivening that is
the more they're able to like actually
become present to it and then choose to
walk into it right but it doesn't seem
to presuppose relate related this in any
kind of sense so I would imagine that if
you kind of use that sense and you bring
it into like a smaller unit of relation
like that'll just be kind of weird
because it's it it's there's a there's a
the reality is a different reality where
you're like oh you're responding well to
one another you're shaping one is out
there they're attune to one another
right that sounds like C I think it's
kind of like what even would have you be
more related like is public because it'd
be inspiring to be
but the inspiration would be him listed
the way that you were interacting and
not understanding that person right yeah
it's like I feel like we we've touched
on the cart beam before the horse a
number of times here the intention of
being therapeutic as opposed to the
intention of hearing the intention of
seeing and reverent scene and present
scene as the intention as opposed to
utility improvement right supplements
yeah right rice burner modern think it's
like it i thou i it right like it means
to an end
and an end in itself it's right in there
but like both of them are both of them
are like that if i had to relate to
everything as a vow every moment the day
i couldn't like leave my bedroom like oh
the wall whoa whoa you are wall it's a
it's a categorical mistake right but you
know I think what the way that we're
related to people right car oh my god
such a huge bad mushroom trip what our
laws oh my god what is car exactly
exactly exactly even that's why mushroom
trips you just you can't you can't have
a life if you're high in mushrooms
because everything is so filled with
bonus right yeah so that the complexity
is so much more obvious and we can't
even we can't even operate we got a dumb
shit down like we're like we need to
pixelate this picture otherwise I can't
leave my bedroom yeah totally yeah okay
why are you hugging the wall yes it's so
unique
I can't believe I am I spent my whole
life not seeing this yeah yes yes so
that quality of just like in a certain
sense if you used to imagine likely I
think that's it's not like it's not like
you don't kick his ass right baby that's
the appropriate thing it's not like you
don't call him out in weather or
whatever's in the way of him being
committed to like that's one of the
things that woods like most of the time
in relationship with other people were
like the main way of being related to
other people is because we're mutually
comported towards a possibility right
we're trying to like work on a project
we're like trying to get something in
the world we're dealing with something
right there's that kind of triangular
sense right so we look at things as a
means to the end of that right however
all of that right is grounded in an
either relation if this I've our
relationship isn't there our ability to
respond to each other in this revealing
of this possibility structure become
diminished right it happens in companies
all the time or it happens in teams all
the time it's the inner subjective
relationship breaks down like like there
isn't the possibility goes away so I
think it's a matter of like not all the
time right just like being like oh my
god right it's but but but on some the
ability to go into I though of like who
are you like oh yeah I'm assuming things
about you but what's actually going on
with you right oh I had no idea oh I see
how that would occur for you Oh what I'm
getting about you is this now I'm
feeling regret for what I was doing I
really apologize for that like that kind
of sense of like where you can drop into
I though right in in review like
oftentimes of breakdowns that way that's
what happens right like when when a
breakdown happens and you're frustrated
with each other and then if you can
actually not fight forget interested
right and have a mutual self-disclosure
those are the things that then just like
when you come out of that you look back
at the thing the consider the thing that
York imported to you together and it
glows so much more right with more
possibility and you'd seed new things
right so it's like that the ability to
do that and I think circling basically
is a yoga of that it's a yoga of being
able to like be able to like kind of
tolerate the anxiety of that move
towards intimacy not like like to move
through all those things like
frustration and be able to stay in
relationship and and open up through it
yesterday with Gregg I told him all the
ways that I'm terrified right now and
anxious and all these things and he
guided me through this framework this
cognitive framework that he's developed
and taught for years and years and it
made this joke at the end of the
interview about whether or not he could
take my insurances payment for that and
he told me that he had considered for a
long time giving up his license as a
clinical psychologist because this shit
should not be clinical well this stuff
needs to be in every house in every
relationship there ought be frameworks
that we can understand each other better
that we can hold space for each other
better that we can that our
relationships can be more therapeutic in
general because we're all so deeply in
need of it we're all still dealing with
the turmoil of our adolescence and our
parental relationships and their
shortcomings and shortcomings of our
society in our history and our genetics
and all of this shit and yeah I'm really
super glad we connected on this I'm
really glad that you
that you went deep enough to figure out
what it was about those interactions
that you had years ago that made it
potent that made it important that made
it powerful that made it
transformational and that you did the
work to figure that out so that you
could share it because it's it's very
helpful for me and I can see it's it's
illuminating for me and I said that it
hit me in the head like a brick because
it's an illuminating in a way that is
promising and painful simultaneously
it's illuminating the promise of the
future in the pain of the past like uh
yeah talk that up
Oh yep that marriage yep I definitely
fucked that up yeah so like guy thanks
fucker but it also is like when I think
about just societally if we just zoom
out to think of individuals and groups
the need the just innate and incredibly
powerful not only desire but like need
to be seen need to be heard need to be
held need to be understood emotionally
and cognitively and historically and and
have space for our own experience
created by another person yeah and to
have someone be curious about us this is
like this is what is being this is
what's being called out for I feel and I
don't think that most of the people who
are yelling the loudest about what is
happening
actually no what they're calling for
yeah yeah and I don't even in this
conversation I feel like a huge amount
of clarity as to what is being called
for and what I might do to to answer
that as far as be as as far as being a
person who is in a position that I can
create space for other people's
experience and I think that there's a
big there's a part of me that literally
like in the last couple of weeks I'm
like I want to push back against the
guilt that I feel like is being
purported in my direction say no I'm not
a slave owner no I'm not a racist no
stop telling me that no this is not my
this is not my fault I am NOT
responsible for the world I'm not
responsible for the problems of the
world this is not my you can't fucking
put this on me you can't put this on me
you can't put this on me and this is
like the first this is the first
epiphany that we talked about this
predisposition to take everything
personally yeah instead of taking a step
back and be like oh what is actually
being said here yeah because there is a
lot of blame there is a lot of blaming
language but but that's the blame the
blame makes sense the blame makes sense
you have a fucking listen to me for four
hundred fucking years right and so it
comes out as I think that it seems in my
own experiences is that it comes out as
like guilt as it comes out as like an
accusation that we internalize as guilt
and then the guilt gets algorithmically
amplified to a level that the vast
majority of people cannot handle and
have to step out of the way and say no
this must not be a problem no this must
be a lie
no this is not my fucking fault
and I don't know man like I I only I
have a handful of black friends man and
these guys have a pretty fucking good
they have pretty fucking good they are
they they do what they want for the vast
majority of what I know and I don't I
guess right now okay so like what
exactly so so your so yours you're
speaking of that hat right like when you
said I had a handful of black friends
you're addressing a concern where's the
concern coming from who are you
addressing exactly a bunch of white
people of Internet yeah seed seats like
it's like it it's suck it's not even
it's a sense of it's hard to even say is
it mmm-hmm like like there's no one even
to address exactly right nebulous but
there's there's a an urgency that once
has you want to act but nothing to act
upon exactly
uh-huh right so just just seeing that
like just looking at that you know I
don't know if there's anything to do
about though they're just kind of like
looking at that going what like what
what's that that's strange
exactly yeah that's a new wall to hug
yeah but I have this some you know I I
thought is something my dad my dad who's
a recovering alcoholic he got sober I
was twelve he got really involved in a
and he's you know has he sponsors people
and all that kind of stuff and one time
he told this story where where this guy
comes up to him that he that he had
sponsored apparently years ago right and
guy comes up and he's just like hey I
left before I could tell you about I've
been why I lost touch with you but I
wanted to say that thing that you said
to me when he said that that revealed
everything differently it changed my
life it had me moved it ended up my I'm
so much happier than her right and and
he gets done and they hug and my dad
walks away and he's like he
misunderstood what I said there's this
quality of like what like and I think
that story funnily exemplifies a real
truth that like I don't even know like
there's something else going on here
that's a lot more mysterious than me
right like well who's to say like you
know it's a funny situation well oh you
misunderstood me I'm gonna correct you
well is that really more true or is it
more true what he heard yeah right so
there's this kind of way that like if
you look at with my dad my dad just
showed up and he was himself and he like
really was in that conversation and he
took people on and he cared for the
people that he could actually his body
could comport to right he there's a way
in which were like I think this this
this thing that Nora said has just
really been playing you know you know
how you get these somebody says
something you know like ah that's
interesting but didn't Wiggles in you
write its thing the North verses that's
like the biggest change system change
happens the place it happens at is in
the smallest intimate relation okay and
it's interesting that is like
pragmatically like the would to be a
human is to be thrown into an intimate
relationship of a world and you kind of
arrive and you you arrive and by the
time you wake up you're already have a
first name and a last name that you
didn't pick with a boatload of concerns
and social things and you're already
enacting it begun and then you kind of
become aware of it right and like so
much about
human life is about coping like we
become who we are with how we respond to
be alive everything I'm doing is a
response well it's I think it's really
important and it's really easy to lose
this on the internet in this way that
you don't even notice it
we're like no there's like how you
become you is through coping with your
chosen and thrown into concerns of the
world that's how you realize your
character in the world realizes itself
through you to bring your full attention
to those relations and actually like the
stoic thing right which I think that's
really brilliant right where they're
like look you have very little agency
it's like barely barely distinguishable
like you should probably direct it
towards the things that you're actually
can make a difference on right it's not
obvious right that's rationality to
ration for what actually my attention
can actually make a difference on and
like define those things right and then
bring your attention and concern and
commitments into those things so that
they can maybe open up beyond themselves
and that you mutually realize your world
as it really realizes you in that
exchange you can almost think about like
the the internet on some level social
media is like an it's like a dyslexic
stoicism like here's all the things your
agency is gigantic your reach is global
the most deeply embedded systemic
failures of humanity are at your
fingertips you lazy white cocksucker guy
Y hugging the wall get up and fucking
fix the world
you know things I think that there are
ways is like where technology is
actually bringing something more
available that he's more technology
which are these conversations yeah like
I can't think of like a less
technological thing that a meandering
conversation hey and it's there's
something in these this is a part of the
internet that I think it actually starts
to show the potential of it I think yeah
well thanks for doing this yeah it's
been really fun man
nice to getting to know you yeah nice
getting to know you too guy do it again
my life is my moment my life is calling
me to cope with it right now so yeah
mine too thanks man
thanks where where can we find where can
we find more stuff the more of your work
and more information about circling so
couple of things I the company that I
own is called the circling Institute and
we offer like circling weekly it's all
online right now so there's like a
Thursday night circling that anyone can
come to we have weekend events and the
main thing that we do is a year-long
training program called the art of
circling that's all online now and so
I'll give you the link for it the
circling Institute com
I also I have a YouTube channel where I
get really cool people on and we have
these kinds of conversations and that's
just guys saying suck on YouTube and if
you want to contact me personally just
email me a guy sink stock at gmail.com
love it love it do me a favor connect me
with Norah Bates and sounds like I
needed to talk to her yeah totally well
okay guy love you man thank you yeah you
too
and I'll send you the I'll send you all
the links and stuff so you can post it
great great all right looking good times
look back see you